<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>&pandora; installation</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>
      &pandora; is not only a single app, its composed by
      several shellscript files (Unix Agents), a WEB application in
      PHP (Console), some code in C++ (Windows Agent), some code in
      PERL5 (Server) and some structure and data in SQL (Database),
      so, to get all this running you need to have some pieces of
      software installed in your system. This is a list of packages,
      libraries and software you need before install &pandora;.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Pandora Servers</title>
    <para>
      Pandora 1.2 has three kind of servers: Data server, Network
      Server and SNMP Server/Trap console. All of them could be
      installed in the same machine or in different machines, also,
      you could setup many of them in a High Availability enviroment
      or using it to manage highs loads of data.
    </para>
    <sect2><title>Pandora Data Server</title>
    <para>
      To build <emphasis>Pandora Data Server</emphasis> you need to
      have the following perl modules and software installed in your
      machine. This packages could be installed using your
      distribution packaging system or using CPAN.
      <blockquote>
	<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	  <listitem><para>XML::Simple, useful XML functions
	  </para></listitem>
  	  <listitem><para>Digest::MD5, MD5 generation
	  </para></listitem>
  	  <listitem><para>Time::Local, Date and Time basic manipulation
	  </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>DBI, DB interface with MySQL
	  </para></listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Date::Manip, needed to manipulate Date and Time formats
	      of input, output and compare
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </blockquote>
    </para>
    <para>
      You can find them at http://www.cpan.org or install using your
      default package instalation system. These packages are in the
      default distribution of Suse 9.1 and Debian 3.0 GNU/Linux. Also
      available for Solaris in CPAN repository. If you use Windows go
      to http://ppm.activestate.com. Or you can use the ppm tool to
      download the modules:
      <programlisting>
	ppm install DBI
	ppm install DBD-mysql
	ppm install Datemanip
      </programlisting>
      Next, you need to set the TZ (Time Zone) environment
      variable. In Windows: set TZ=WET (for example)
    </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Pandora Network Server</title>
    <para>
      Requires SSH Server and Perl v5.8 or higher and the next Perl Modules:
       <blockquote>
	<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      IO::Socket, manage and manipulation of TCP/UDP sockets
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
  	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Time::HiRes, needed for ICMP times
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
  	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Time::Local, Date and Time basic manipulation
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      SNMP, for SNMP management
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Date::Manip, needed to manipulate Date and Time formats
	      of input, output and compare
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Net::Ping, to calculate latency times (it's required
	      that the server runs as root user).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
       </blockquote>
       To use SNMP fuctions it's needed also to have installed the
       net-snmp package. It's worth to say that to run modules of
       GENERIC_ICMP_DATA type (calculate ICMP latency time) Pandora
       Network Server must run with root privileges.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Pandora SNMP Server</title>
    <para>
      You need to install the NET-SNMP package which is included in
      all GNU/Linux distributions. You have to use the snmptrapd
      binary and copy or link it to $HOME_PANDORA/util, where
      $HOME_PANDORA is the instalation directory of Pandora.
    </para>
    <para>
      This binary gets the SNMP traps, generating a log that is
      parsed by the Pandora Server.
    </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Installing Pandora Server</title>
    <para>
      Create the <filename>/opt/pandora</filename> directory and
      "gunzip" and "untar" here the
      <filename>pandora_server_1.2.tar.gz</filename> file.
    </para>
    <para>
      Create an user pandora in OS. Usually you do that (in GNU/Linux)
      with commands:
      <programlisting>
	useraddd pandora -d /home/pandora
	mkdir /home/pandora
	chown pandora /home/pandora
      </programlisting>
      This user will be used by the SSH transfers to the server, so
      this user will need a strong password.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the file
      <filename>/home/pandora/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> we will
      add the public key of each agent which send data to Pandora
      Server. These keys must be SSH v2, OpenSSH DiffieHellman (DF) or
      RSA. To convert between keys you can use the ssh-keygen tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      Pandora Server will check and parse XML files sent by Pandora
      Agents and will insert the data into the Database.
      </para>
    <para>
      Check launch scripts (pandora_network, pandora_server,
      pandora_snmp) and check for pathnames in the first two variables
      in script.  roa Server. This usually is
      <filename>/opt/pandora_server</filename>
    </para>
  </sect2>
    
  <sect2><title>Configuring your new Pandora Server setup</title>
  <para>
    After install Pandora Server in, you will need to edit the file
    <filename>pandora_server.conf</filename>, where are defined the
    variables of the server configuration. File
    <filename>pandora_server.conf</filename> is a text file, you could
    edit with your prefer text editor, like emacs. This configuration
    file is common to all kinds of Pandora Server (Data server, SNMP
    Server, Network server), you also could have different copies of
    configuration file for each Pandora Server you have.
  </para>
  <para>
    Edit configuration file of Pandora Server, usually
    <filename>/opt/pandora/conf/pandora_server.conf</filename> and
    take a look at the lines:
    <programlisting>
      dbuser pandora
      dbpass pandora
      dbhost localhost
    </programlisting>
    Please change them to your own data. For security reasons isn't
    recommended use the default values. If you run Pandora Server in
    Windows, you need to use the backslash twice in $dirname, that is:
    "\\", for example: my
    $dirname="C:\\pandora\\pandora_server\\data_in";, not needed in
    $log_file.
  </para>
  <para>
    These are default values, and all must be existing directory and
    filename and valid username, password and hostname.
  </para>
  <para>
    Remember: you need to create the directory /opt/pandora/data_in
    where Pandora Server will read and write data, sent by remote
    agents using ssh/scp. This directory must be owned or with
    permissions to write for user "pandora". If you dont have a
    "pandora" user yet, create it.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can run Pandora Server with an user without privilegues, you
    can use the user "pandora", it only needs to run /usr/bin/perl and
    access to <filename>/opt/pandora</filename> and
    <filename>/opt/pandora/data_in</filename> directories.
  </para>
  <para>
    This is true with all the components but with Pandora SNMP Console
    needs root user to open UDP port 161 (this can be solved setting
    SUID0 to the snmptrapd binary) and running the rest of the Server
    using an user without privileges.
  </para>
  <para>
    Also Pandora Network Server can be run using an user without
    privileges, but the GENERIC_ICMP_DATA type won't work, as root
    privileges are required to get ICMP latency times.
  </para>
  <para>
    Check the MySQL connection with the user and password before running the server
  </para>
  <para>
    Pandora Server distribution tarball includes a Posix/System V
    start/stop script for "daemonize" Pandora Server. It is possible
    that you need to customize, but its runs smoothly on GNU/Linux
    (debian, Suse) and Solaris 8 systems. It has start|stop|restart
    parameters to include it in your default init level directory and
    it creates a logfile defined in $log_file variable (by default is
    <filename>/opt/pandora/pandora.log</filename>):
    <programlisting>
      /etc/init.d/pandora_server start
    </programlisting>
  </para>

    <sect3><title>Setting up SSH configuration</title>
    <para>
      Pandora, uses SSH protocol to copy XML data packets,
      generated by the agents, to the server. You need to generate a
      SSH2 key in every agent, and copy the public key in
      <filename>/home/pandora/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>, so you
      need to create a user called "pandora" withour privileges. This
      user will be used by agents to copy data into Pandora Data Server
      <filename>/opt/pandora/data_in</filename> directory.
    </para>
    <para>
      Please BE SURE that user "pandora" exists (if not, create with
      useradd), and
      <filename>/home/pandora/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> exists and
      ownership of this file and directory is for pandora user, and
      permissions set to 600.
    </para>
    <para>
      Please be sure that directory
      <filename>/opt/pandora/data_in</filename> exists and pandora
      user is able to write in.
    </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
    
  <sect1>
    <title>Pandora Console and Pandora database</title>
    <sect2><title>Pandora database install</title>
    <para>
      Please look at MySQL install and management guide
      (http://dev.mysql.com/doc) to obtain information about how to
      create a MySQL database, how to manage mysql users and give
      him/her privileges to read/write in Pandora database. Remember
      that you must write the password of the root user in MySQL
      database to enter mysql command line. This user is not the same
      of the Operating System. The root password in MySQL is in blank
      by default (within almost all distributions), you must changed
      this password with the MySQL command
      <filename>mysqladmin</filename>. Please be careful with this.
    </para>
    <para>
      You need a database with name "pandora", you could rename it, but
      you need to reconfigure in server too.
    </para>
    <para>
      To create the structure of Pandora database in MySQL Server you
      have the SQL script "pandoradb.sql".
    </para>
    <para>
      It creates tables and indexes needed to insert information into
      Pandora database.
    </para>
    <para>
      You MUST populate database with SQL script "pandoradb_data.sql",
      it inserts data needed to run Web Console and default user
      (login: admin, pass: pandora) to access Pandora Web Console.
    </para>
    <para>
      First create a database called "pandora", and set an user to be
      able to access this database:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
      mysql> create database pandora;
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      Later, execute the next commands using a user with enough
      privileges to create tables and indexes for pandora Database into
      your MySQL Server:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
      cat pandoradb.sql | mysql -D pandora -u root -p
      cat pandoradb_data.sql | mysql -D pandora -u root -p
    </programlisting>
    <para>	
      Note: if your system is Windows, use the command type instead of
      cat.
    </para>
    <para>	
      You can also use the source command, if you are connected to
      MySQL, from the MySQL prompt:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
      mysql> use babel
      mysql> source path_to_babel_dbstruct.sql
      mysql> source path_to_babel_dbdata.sql
    </programlisting>
    <para>	
      This example is valid using root user in
      MySQL<footnote><para>Remember if you're in Windows use the
      double slash ("//") with the path to the files, not the
      backslash ("\").</para></footnote>
    </para>
    <para>
      Now we will create an user "pandora" and will be given to it
      privileges from the localhost:
      <programlisting>
	mysql> grant all on pandora.* to 'pandora'@'localhost'
	identified by 'pandora';
      </programlisting>
      Keep in mind that users need access from Pandora WEB Console and
      from Pandora Server, if your deployment has many subcomponents
      in different physical machines, you need to setup a MySQL user
      with privileges to access from different locations.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you get the error "Warning: mysql_connect()
      [function.mysql-connect]: client does not support authentication
      protocol requested by server; consider upgrading" when
      authenticating Web Console, you have to change the way the
      password is stored into the database:
      <programlisting>
	mysql> set password for 'babel'@'localhost' = old_password('babel');
      </programlisting>
      Please note this user will be used by several babel
      subcomponents(babel Server, babel Web Console) to access
      database.
    </para>
    </sect2>

    
    <sect2>
      <title>Pandora console install.</title>
      <para>Prior to install Pandora console, you need the following
      dependencies and software needed:
      <blockquote>
	<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Web server. Apache2 is recommended.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      PHP 4.3.x, or PHP 5.x. Both has been tested for Pandora 1.2
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      PHP Modules for MySQL, GD, session management and SNMP.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      JpGraph, it is necesary to generate graphics. It has an
	      open source license, you can download it in
	      http://www.aditus.nu/jpgraph/
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </blockquote>
      </para>
      <para>
	To install Pandora Console, simply untar in your HTTP server
	publishing directory and set perms to www-data or http user.
      </para>
      <para>
	To setup Pandora Console, you only need to modify a file,
	<filename>include/config.php</filename>, where the following
	variables are included in .php code:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
	$dbname="pandora";   // name of database for pandora)
	$dbuser="pandora";   // mysql user to access db
	$dbpassword="pandora";   // Password for mysql user
	$dbhost="pandora";   // Hostname or IP of mySQL server
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	If database is defined and was correctly installed, you can
	now access:
	<programlisting>
	  http://hoste:port/installdir/index.php
	</programlisting>
	The first time you log there is a default admin user "admin"
	and password "pandora". It's worth to say that <emphasis>YOU
	MUST CHANGE CREDENTIALS BEFORE LOGIN FIRST TIME</emphasis>,
	change it or create another account, give it administrator
	privileges, and disable this one.
      </para>      
      <para>
	<graphic fileref="images/pandora_login.jpg" scale="70" align="center"/>
	If you cannot see a screen like this, it's possible that you
	have problems with PHP instalation. When you installed the
	Web, please check that PHP engine its running. Fist try to
	access to the server IP with a browser. You must see the
	Welcome Apache page.
      </para>
      <para>
	Remember that alter installing the PHP and the PHP module for
	Apache you must stop and start the Server Apache. As an
	example, Ubuntu with Apache2:
	<programlisting>
	  /etc/init.d/apache2 stop
	  /etc/init.d/apache2 start
	</programlisting>
	
	To verify the PHP and Apache integration you can create the
	file <filename>test.php</filename> with the following lines:
	<screen>
	  &lt;?PHP
	  echo "&lt;h1&gt;TEST&lt;/h1&gt;";
	  phpinfo();
	  ?&gt;
	</screen>
	Now, copy this file in the Apache HTTPDOC directory. This
	directory depend of the Operating System or Linux
	Distribution, for example in Ubuntu this directory is
	<filename>/var/www</filename> and in SUSE is
	<filename>/srv/www/htdocs</filename>).
      </para>
      <para>
	To check this integration, please use your browser to open the
	following URL:
	<programlisting>
	  http://IP/test.php
	</programlisting>
	
	Where IP is IP Address of your Apache server. If the
	integration is correct you will see in the browser a text
	string with big font: <quote>TEST</quote> and a big table with
	a lot of info about your PHP installation.
      </para>
      <sect3><title>Graphic reporting instalation</title>
      <para>
	For correct graphic generation, you need to enter the full
	path to a TrueType font installed in your system. By default a
	free truetype font is distributed with Pandora Console
	package, and placed in
	<filename>./reporting/FreeSans.ttf</filename> file. Please
	check that setup directive
	<filename>$config_fontpath</filename> is well configured.
      </para>
      <para>
	Pandora 1.2 uses JpGraph for viewing graphics. JpGraph is a
	different project and has no relationship with Pandora, so you
	need to install it. You can find at
	<filename>http://www.aditus.nu/jpgraph/</filename>. Download
	last version (2.x), and place all <filename>.php</filename>
	files from src directory into
	<filename>reporting/jpgraph</filename> Pandora Console
	directory.
      </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  
  <sect1><title>Pandora Agents</title>
  <sect2><title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    &pandora; agents collect all system's data. They are executed in
    each local system, although they can also collect remote
    information by installing monitoring systems for the agent in
    several different machines - called satellite agents.
  </para>
  <para>
    They are developed to work under a given platform, making use of
    the specific tools of the language being used: VBSCript/Windows
    Scripting for Microsoft platforms (Win2000, WinXP y Win2003),
    ShellScripting for UNIX - which includes Linux, Solaris, AIX, HPUX
    and BSD, as well as the Nokia's IPSO. Pandora agents can be
    developed in virtually any language, given its simple API system
    and being open source. There are branches of the Pandora project
    started for the creation of agents in Posix C, Perl and Java for
    those systems requiring closed agents.
  </para>
  <para>
    Pandora Agents are Free Software, i.e., the way agents collect and
    sent information is documented. An agent can be recreated in any
    programming language, and can be upgraded easily, to improve
    aspects of the program not covered so far.
  </para>
  <para>
    This document describes the installation of agents in machines
    running over Windows and Unix operating systems.
  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Generic role of the agents</title>
  <para>
    Regardless the platform an agent is running on, this is formed of
    the following elements: 
  </para>

  <para>
    A script (or binary application in Windows) that collects and
    sends the data to the server. For UNIX machines the script is
    called pandora_agent.sh and is executed directly from the Pandora
    agent folder.
  </para>
  <para>
    One or several configuration files where the values to be
    collected are defined. The file is called pandora_agent.conf both
    for Windows and Unix machines.
  </para>
  <para>
    This simple structure makes it easy the customisation of an
    agent. There is no need to "reprogram" the agent to modify the
    way it works, as the configuration file holds most of the
    parameters needed to do so.
  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Main Script</title>
  <para>
    The main script is the executable file that collects the data
    specified in the configuration file. It sends the data to the
    server in XML. In Windows machines application is installed as a
    service and is executed at the time intervals set in the
    configuration file. In machines running over UNIX the main script
    is run through a special script called pandora_agent_daemon, and
    runs continuously in the machine as a process.
  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Configuration File</title>
  <para>
    The data collection in the host system is the gathering of
    independent data units, which are defined in the
    <filename>pandora_agent.conf</filename> file. The
    pandora_agent.conf file is divided in two parts:
    <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>General parameters</emphasis>: Configure general
	  options about server location, agent name, interval, and
	  other general options.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Module definitions</emphasis>: Configure and
	  define the method of extraction for each piece of
	  information that will be extracted from local host and sent
	  to Pandora Server.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <sect3><title>General parameters</title>
  <para>
    The general parameters of the agent configuration are defined in
    this section. Some of these parameters are common for all systems
    and others specific for Windows or UNIX. The general parameters
    are:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>server_path</emphasis>: (Shared parameter) The
	      server path is the full path of the folder where the
	      server stores the data sent by the agent. It is usually
	      <filename>/opt/pandora/data_in</filename>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>server_ip</emphasis>: (Parameter shared by
	      Windows and Unix agents) The server IP is the IP address
	      or the host name of the Pandora server, where the data
	      will be stored. The host must be reachable and must be
	      listening to port 22 (SSH).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>temporal</emphasis>: (Shared parameter) This
	      is the full path of the folder where the agent stores
	      the data locally, before it is sent to the server. It
	      must be said that the data packages are deleted once the
	      agent tries to contact Pandora server, no matter if the
	      communication was successful or not. This is done to
	      avoid over flooding hard drive of the host system where
	      the agent runs. The location of the local folder varies
	      with the architecture of the host system. In Unix
	      systems this is usually
	      <filename>/opt/pandora/data_out</filename>, and in
	      Windows systems
	      <filename>C:\pandora\data_out</filename>.

	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>interval</emphasis>: (Shared parameter) This
	      is the time interval in seconds in which the agent will
	      collect data from the host system and send the data
	      packages to the server. The recommended value ranges
	      from 300 (5 minutes) to 600 (10 minutes). This number
	      could be larger, although it is important to consider
	      the impact of a larger number on the database.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>debug</emphasis>: (Unix only) This parameter
	      is used to test the connection between agent and server
	      and the correct working condition of the agent. The
	      process consists of a loop, data collection and data
	      transfer. It does not delete any data when the process
	      is finished. The activity is written in a log file,
	      stored in the Pandora root folder. The file is named
	      pandora_agent.log. This log file can be used to test the
	      system and to investigate potential issues.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>agent_name</emphasis>: (Shared parameter) This
	      is an alternative host name. This parameter is optional
	      as if it is not declared the name is obtained directly
	      from the system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>pandora_path</emphasis>: (Unix exclusive
	      parameter) This is then path of the folder where the
	      files of the Pandora agent are stored. This is usually
	      <filename>/opt/pandora</filename> or
	      <filename>/opt/pandora_agent</filename>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>checksum</emphasis>: (Shared parameter).  This parameter
	      can take two values. If the value is 1, the checksums
	      are performed through MD5. If the value is 0, the
	      checksum is not performed at all. This may be useful for
	      systems where a MD5 tool cannot be implemented. If the
	      checksum is deactivated in the agent it must be also
	      disconnected in the server. Otherwise it could create
	      problems.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>  
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    An example of the general parameters from a Unix configuration would be.
    <screen>
      server_ip Pandora_Server
      server_path  /opt/pandora/data_in
      pandora_path /opt/pandora
      temporal /opt/pandora/data_out
      interval 300
      agent_name  satellite_agent
      debug 1
      checksum 1
    </screen>
  </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3><title>Module definition</title>
  <para>
    Each data item that is to be collected must be defined precisely
    in each module, using the exact syntax. As many values as
    necessary can be set to be collected, adding at the end of the
    general parameters as many modules as the number of values to
    collect. Each module is made of several directives. Following is a
    descriptive relation of all module marks available for Unix agents
    (almost all of them are applicable to Windows Agent too).
  </para>
    <sect4><title>module_begin</title>
    <para>
	Defines the beginning of the module.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_name name</title>
    <para>
      Name of the module. This is the id for this module, choose a
      name without blank spaces and not very long. There is no
      practical limitation (max of 250 chars) but will be more easy to
      manage if you use short names. This name CANNOT be duplicated
      with a similar name in the same agent. This name could be
      duplicated with other modules in other agents.
      </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_type type</title>
    <para>
      Data type the module will handle. There are four data types for agents:
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Numeric (generic_data). Simple numeric data, float or
	integer. If the values are of the float type, they will be
	truncated to their integer value.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Incremental (generic_date_inc). Integer numeric data equal to
	    the differential between the actual value and the previous
	    one. When this differential is negative the value is set to 0.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Alphanumeric (generic_string). Text strings up to 255 characters.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Monitors (generic_proc). Stores numerically the status of the
	    processes. This data type is called monitor because it assigns
	    0 to an "Incorrect" status and any value above 0 to any
	    "Correct" status.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </sect4>
    
    <sect4><title>module_exec command</title>
    <para>
      This is the generic "<emphasis>command to execute</emphasis>"
      directive. Both, for Unix and Windows agents there is only one
      directive to obtain data in a generic way, executing a single
      command (you could use pipes for redirecting execution to anoter
      command). This directive executes a command and stores the
      returned value. This method is also available on Windows
      agents. This is the "general purpose method" for both kind of
      agents.
    </para>
    <para>
      For a Windows agent there are more directives to obtain data, who
      are described following this lines.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_service service (Win32 Only)</title>
    <para>
      Checks if a given service name is running in this host. Remember
    to use " " characters if service name contains blank spaces.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_proc process (Win32 Only)</title>
    <para>
      Checks if a given processname is running in this host. Remember
      to use " " characters if process name contains blank spaces.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_freedisk drive_letter: (Win32 Only)</title>
    <para>
      Checks free disk on drive letter (do not forget ":" after drive
      letter.
    </para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4><title>module_cpuusage cpu id  (Win32 Only)</title>
    <para>
      Returns CPU usage on CPU number cpu. If you only have one cpu,
      use 0 as value.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    
    <sect4><title>module_freememory (Win32 Only)</title>
    <para>
      Return free memory in the whole system.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_min value </title>
    <para>
      This is the minimum valid value for the data generated in this
      module. If the module has not yet been defined in the web
      console this value will be taken from this directive. This
      directive is not compulsory. This value does not override the
      value defined in the agent if the module does not exist in the
      management console. It is created automatically when working on
      learning mode.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_max value </title>
    <para>
      It is the maximum valid value for the data generated in this
      module. If the module has not been defined in the web console
      this value will be taken from this directive. This directive is
      not compulsory and is not supported by the Windows agent. This
      value does not override the value defined in the agent if the
      module does not exist in the management console. This is created
      automatically when working on learning mode.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_description text</title>
    <para>
      This directive is used to add a comment to the module. This
      directive is not compulsory. This value does not override the
      value defined in the agent if the module does not exist in the
      management console. This is created automatically when working
      on learning mode.
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_interval factor</title>
    <para>
      Pandora 1.2 introduces this new feature. You can, for each
      module, setup its own interval. This interval its calculated as
      a multiply factor for agent interval. For example, if your agent
      has interval 300 (5 minutes), and you want a module only be
      calculated each 15 minutes, you could add this line:
      <filename>module_interval 3</filename>. So this module will be
      calculated each 300sec x 3 = 900sec (15 minutes).
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>module_end</title>
    <para>
      Ends module definition
    </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4><title>Examples</title>
    <para>
      An example of a Windows module, checking if EventLog service is
      alive, would be:
      <programlisting>
	module_begin
	module_name ServicioReg
	module_type generic_proc
	module_service Eventlog
	module_description Eventlog service availability
	module_end
      </programlisting>
      An example of a Unix module would be:
      <programlisting>
	module_begin
	module_name cpu_user
	module_type generic_data
	module_exec vmstat | tail -1 | awk '{ print $14 }'
	module_min 0
	module_max 100
	module_description User CPU
	module_end
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    </sect4>
  </sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Agent types</title>
<para>
  It is possible to monitor virtually any system with Pandora. This
  can be done either with a local agent collecting data directly from
  the system to be monitored, using a a satellite agent collecting
  data from a system by SNMP or using the new Pandora 1.2 agents, the
  remote agents, who can chack using remote network polling (TCP, UCP,
  ICMP/PING and SNMP) remote services, from the Pandora Network
  Server.
</para>
<para>
  The local agents can be either Windows or Unix agents. The satellite
  agents can be implemented using any of the agents above. The modules
  are configured to collect data from the external system by, for
  example, an SNMPGET tool.
  </para>

<sect3><title>UNIX agents</title>
<sect4><title>Introduction to Unix agents</title>
<para>
  The in-built UNIX applications and tools make the agents running on
  this system be very simple. There are also agents developed for AIX,
  Linux, Solaris and BSD platforms, some of them very similar but not
  identical.  Requirements for the installation of Pandora Agents on
  UNIX
  </para>
  <sect5><title>AIX</title>
  <para>
    MD5 signatures are used to guarantee the integrity of the
    generated data packages. The MD5 package is integrated in AIX 5.1
    and above. There is a freeware package for AIX 4.3 but it has
    several issues and might not work correctly. In the case of having
    problems with the AIX agents the checksum system used to validate
    the integrity of the data can be disabled.
  </para>
  </sect5>
  <sect5><title>Solaris</title>
  <para>
    The MD5 package is necessary to execute the Solaris agent
    correctly. This package is available from http://sunfreeware.com
    . It can be also downloaded for Solaris 8 from the following URL:
  </para>
  <para>
    ftp://ftp.sunfreeware.com/pub/freeware/sparc/8/md5-6142000-sol8-sparc-local.gz
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>MD5 Package installation on Solaris</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
    <programlisting>
      root@stest:/tmp:> gzip -d md5-6142000-sol8-sparc-local.gz
      root@stest:/tmp:> pkgadd -d ./md5-6142000-sol8-sparc-local
      
      The following packages are available:
      1  SMCmd5     md5
      (sparc) 6142000

      Select package(s) you wish to process (or 'all' to process
      all packages). (default: all) [?,??,q]: 1
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para><emphasis>Solaris SSH</emphasis></para>
  <para>
    The suggested SSH client is OpenSSH. If any other SSH client is to
    be used it must be considered that each piece software may have
    different ways to generate or manage keys. For example, if
    F-Secure SSH is used, the public key must be in OpenSSH format
    when the keys are generated. The format can be changed from IETF
    to OpenSSH with F-Secure SSH, using the following command:
  </para>
  <para>
    <filename>
      ssh-keygen -i -f file_ietf_pubkey
    </filename>
  </para>
  </sect5>

  <sect5><title>GNU/Linux</title>
  <para>
    SSH and MD5 should be installed in Linux by default, but if they
    are not they can be installed using the tools available in each
    distribution.
  </para>
  </sect5>
  <sect5><title>BSD (IPSO)</title>
  <para>
    SSH and MD5 should be installed by default. If they are not, it is
    necessary to install them.
  </para>
  </sect5>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Pandora Unix Agent install</title>
<para>
  The software comes in a .tar.gz file. First of all the file needs
  to be extracted into a folder, usually /opt/pandora_agent,
  although any other folder may be used. If a different folder is
  used, the daemon launcher must be modified by changing route to
  $PANDORA_HOME.
</para>
<para>
  There is hardly any difference between AIX, Solaris and Linux, and
  they all work around the hash MD5 generation binaries.
</para>
<para>
  This is the structure of the installation in /opt/pandora_agent/
  once the files have been extracted:
</para>
<para>
  <filename>/opt/pandora_agent/data_out</filename>, folder where the
  data collected by the agents is stored.
  </para>
  <para>
    <filename>/opt/pandora_agent/doc</filename>, folder with
    information about the agent and its license.
  </para>
  <para>
    <filename>/opt/pandora_agent/pandora_agent.conf</filename>, file
    where the data to be collected is defined, along side the command
    to be executed for the data collection. This is the system 
    core, as it defines the main data to be collected in any Firewall.
  </para>
  <para>
    <filename>/opt/pandora_agent/pandora_user.conf</filename>, file
    where several of the parameters to collect data from the monitored
    system are defined in more detail.
  </para>
  <para>
    <filename>/opt/pandora_agent/pandora_agent.sh</filename>, this is
    the actual Pandora agent. This file is a shellscript that collects
    the data configured in the pandora_agent.conf and
    pandora_user.conf files. It also transfers the data packages to
    the Pandora server.
  </para>
  <para>
    <filename>/opt/pandora_agent/pandora_agent_daemon</filename>,
    start and stop script. It makes a call to pandora_agent.sh. It
    offers two options, start and stop.
  </para>
  <para>
    <filename>/opt/pandora_agent/pandora.log</filename>, text file
    where the activity of the Pandora agent is saved, when the agent
    is executed in debugging mode.
  </para>
  <sect3><title>Key generation</title>
  <para>
    The SSH keys generated must be:
    <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      SSSH version2 keys
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open SSH format keys
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      DiffieHellman (DH) format keys
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    To generate the keys the command ssh-keygen is executed followed
    by the specific parameters for our operating system. Please,
    create key WITHOUT password.
  </para>
  <para>
    The public key must be copied into the
    <filename>/home/.pandora/authorized_keys</filename> file in the
    Pandora server. Before starting the Pandora agent the SSH
    authentication must be checked. To do this the following command
    must be executed on the agent machine:
    <programlisting>
      $ ssh pandora@pandora_server
    </programlisting>
    
    The system must connect successfully BEFORE launching the Pandora agent.
  </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3><title>First execution of the Unix agent</title>
  <para>
    To start the agent it is only necessary to execute
    pandora_agent_daemon start from /opt/pandora_client. Pandora Agent
    creates a file (/var/run/pandora.pid) with the PID number of the
    process when it is started.
  </para>
  <para>
    For IPSO systems the agent will be started with a nice -10
    priority, so it becomes the process with the lowest priority over
    the system CPU. It will be executed when no other processes with a
    higher priority are waiting in the system CPU queue.
  </para>
  <para>
    In BSD systems the maximum priority is +20 and the lowest -20.
  </para>
  <para>
    To stop agent, execute pandora_agent_daemon stop from /opt/pandora_agent.
  </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3><title>Advanced agent configuration for Unix</title>
  <para>
    The real power of Pandora resides in the capability of the agents
    to run user defined scripts. This could be used to collect
    specific data or to perform an operation to return any desired
    value. This is the purpose of pandora_user.conf.
  </para>
  <para>
    This file is executed every in agent loop. It is a shell-script in
    which any command can be executed, as long as the output is in the
    XML format the agent uses to send data to the server. The XML
    structure would be:
    <programlisting>
      &lt;module&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;NAME&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;type&gt;TYPE&lt;/type&gt;
      &lt;data&gt;DATA&lt;/data&gt;
      &lt;/module&gt;
    </programlisting>

    Where NAME, TYPE and DATA are the variables already defined in
    previous sections. The XML must be built manually, usually using
    echo commands.
  </para>
  <para>
    For example, this would be the script a customized agent would use
    for Checkpoint FW1 in IPSO agents:
    <programlisting>
      #!/bin/sh
      # Pandora User-Defined acquisition script
      # This code is under GPL licence
      # Please refer documentation for more example and a more
      # depth usage instructions

      # mbuf clusters usados (%)
      MBUF_TOTAL=`netstat -m |grep "mbuf cluster" | tr -s "/" " " |awk '{ print $2 }'`
      MBUF_USED=`netstat -m |grep "mbuf cluster" | tr -s "/" " " |awk '{ print $1 }'`
      MBUF_USED_PER=`echo $MBUF_TOTAL $MBUF_USED |  awk '{ print $2 / ($1 / 100) }
      
      echo "&lt;module&gt;"
      echo "&lt;name&gt;MBUF_CLUSTER_USED_PER&lt;/name&gt;"
      echo "&lt;data&gt;$MBUF_USED_PER&lt;/data&gt;"
      echo "&lt;type&gt;generic_data&lt;/type&gt;"
      echo "&lt;/module&gt;"
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>      
    A more complex example could be:
    <screen>
      <![CDATA[
      #!/bin/sh
      # Pandora User-Defined acquisition script
      # This code is under GPL licence
      # Please refer documentation for more example and a more
      # depth usage instructions
	
      # Calculating the number of packages generated by ETH2,
      # if nothing is generated 
      # within 20 seconds an alert is rosen
      # Perform the calculation between 8 to 23h. Return ok for times
      # outside this range 
      
      echo "<module>"
      echo "<name>Packet_Generator_Check</name>"
      echo "<type>generic_proc</type>"
      UNO=`ifconfig eth2 | grep "TX packets" | cut -f 2 -d ":" | grep -o -e "[0-9]*"`
      sleep 20
      DOS=`ifconfig eth2 | grep "TX packets" | cut -f 2 -d ":" | grep -o -e "[0-9]*"`
      HORA=`date "+%k"`
      if [ "$HORA" -lt "8" ] && [ "$HORA" -gt "11" ]
      then
      # Time out of range, no checking, everything OK
      # Fuera de hora, no compruebo, esta OK
         echo "<data>1</data>"
      else
	    if [ "$UNO" == "$DOS" ]
	    then
   	        echo "<data>0</data>"
	    else
	        echo "<data>1</data>"
	    fi
	  fi
	    echo "</module>"
	]]>
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3><title>Implementation examples for Unix Agents</title>
  <para>
    Example #1: calculate the number of HITS of the main page of an
    Apache Web server:
    <programlisting>
      module_begin
      module_name WEB_Hits
      module_type generic_data_inc
      module_exec cat /var/log/apache/access.log | grep "index" | wc -l
      module_end
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
    Example: check if the process of the DNS server (named) is active
    or fell over:
    <programlisting>
      module_begin
      module_name DNS_Daemon
      module_type generic_proc
      module_exec ps -Af | grep named | grep -v "grep" | wc -l
      module_end
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
    Complete example of the configuration of an agent for Linux
    <programlisting>
      # General Parameters
      # ==================
      
      server_ip 		192.168.100.45
      server_path 	/opt/pandora/data_in
      pandora_path 	/opt/pandora_ng/
      temporal    	/opt/pandora_ng/data_out
      interval    	300
      hostname		linuxbox01
      debug			0
      checksum		1
      
      # Module Definition
      # =================
      
      module_begin
      module_name cpu_user
      module_type generic_data
      module_exec vmstat 1 2 | tail -1 | awk '{ print $14 }'
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name cpu_sys
      module_type generic_data
      module_exec vmstat 1 2 | tail -1 | awk '{ print $14 }'
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name disk_root_free
      module_type generic_data
      module_exec df -kh / | tail -1 | awk '{ print 100 - $5 }'
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name disk_store_free
      module_type generic_data
      module_exec df -kh /store  | tail -1 | awk '{ print 100 - $5 }'
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name memfree
      module_type generic_data
      module_exec cat /proc/meminfo  | grep MemFree | cut -c 10-23
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name memused
      module_type generic_data
      module_exec cat /proc/meminfo | grep "Active"  | cut -c 8- | cut -f 1 -d "k"
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name proctotal
      module_type generic_data
      module_exec ps -A | wc -l
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name sshd
      module_type generic_proc
      module_exec ps -Af | grep sshd | grep -v "grep" | wc -l
      
      module_begin
      module_name WEB_Hits
      module_type generic_data_inc
      module_exec cat /var/log/apache/access.log | grep "index.php" | wc -l
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name eMails_proc
      module_type generic_data_inc
      module_exec cat /var/log/mail/mail.log | grep "message-id" | wc -l
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name FTP_sessions
      module_type generic_data_inc
      module_exec cat /var/log/syslog | grep "FTP session opened" | wc -l
      module_end
      
      module_begin
      module_name eMails_SPAM
      module_type generic_data_inc
      module_exec cat /var/log/mail/mail.log | grep "identified spam" | wc -l
      module_end      
    </programlisting>
  </para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Pandora Windows Agents.</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>Build Windows Agent from sources</title>
      <para>
	In order to build from sources, you will need the latest
	Dev-Cpp IDE version, with the MinGW tools. Download from
	http://www.bloodshed.net/devcpp.html
      </para>
      <para>
	Open PandoraService.dev with Dev-Cpp and construct the
	project. Everything should compile fine in a default
	installation.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Windows Agent installation</title>		
      <para>
	Before running or installation of Pandora Windows service, you
	must create the configuration directory and extract the
	PandoraBin.zip file into it.
	
	It doesn't matter where it is installled, because Pandora Agent
	will adapt to any local directory. In the examples, the
	application will be installed in <filename>C:\Pandora\</filename>
      </para>
      <para>
	This directory will hold the configuration files, which are:
	<screen>
	  c:\Pandora\pandora_agent.conf   :: Pandoramain configuration
	  c:\Pandora\id_dsa             :: Private SSH key 
	  c:\Pandora\id_dsa.pub         :: Public SSH key
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Notice: At this moment, the installation of the Pandora Windows
	Agent must be done manually. We are working in a auto-install
	package.
      </para>
      <para>
	To install the Pandora Windows Agent execute this sentence in a
	Windows command line:
	
	<programlisting>
	  PandoraService.exe  --install
	</programlisting>
	
	The Agent will be installed into the Windows services
	system. You can check it on Control Panel -> Administrative
	tools -> Services.
      </para>
      <para>
	To run the Agent open the "Services" dialog (Control Panel ->
	Administrative tools-> Services), search the "Pandora Service"
	service and run it clicking the play button. To stop the
	service, open the "Services" dialog, search the "Pandora
	Service" and click the stop button.
      </para>
      <para>
	To uninstall the Pandora Windows Agent, execute this sentence in
	a Windows command line:
	<programlisting>
	  PandoraService.exe --uninstall
	</programlisting>
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Windows Agent testing</title>
      <para>
	You can check the Pandora Windows Agent output in the
	<filename>C:\babel\babel-debug.dbg</filename> file, that is a
	plain text file and includes info about the execution flow of
	the Agent.
      </para>
      <para>
	To test that SSH is working correctly, you can use the
	--test-ssh parameter in the executable file. This force babel
	to conect using internal SSH and copy a file called
	"ssh.test".
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Windows Agent configuration</title>
      <para>
	All setup is made in <filename>babel_agent.conf</filename>.
	This file is a list of keys/values pairs. Here is an example
	of this file.
	<screen>
	  # General Parameters
	  # ==================
	  
	  server_ip 127.0.0.1
	  server_path /opt/pandora_server/data_in
	  temporal "D:\temp"
	  interval 1
	  agent_name localhost
	  
	  # Module Definition
	  # =================
	  
	  
	  # Counting OpenedConnections (check the language string)
	  module_begin
	  module_name OpenNetConnections
	  module_type generic_data
	  module_exec netstat -na | grep ESTAB | wc -l | tr -d " "
	  module_description Conexiones abiertas (interval 2)
	  module_interval 2
	  module_end
	  
	  # Is Schedule service running ?
	  module_begin
	  module_name ServicioProg
	  module_type generic_proc
	  module_service Schedule
	  module_description Servicio Programador de tareas
	  module_end
	  
	  # Is Eventlog service running ?
	  module_begin
	  module_name ServicioReg
	  module_type generic_proc
	  module_service Eventlog
	  module_description Servicio Registro de sucesos
	  module_end
	  
	  # Is lsass.exe process alive ?
	  module_begin
	  module_name Proc_lsass
	  module_type generic_proc
	  module_proc "lsass.exe"
	  module_description Proceso LSASS.exe
	  module_end
	  
	  # Received packets
	  module_begin
	  module_name ReceivedPackets
	  module_type generic_data
	  module_exec netstat -s | grep  "Paquetes recibidos  "|
	              tr -d " " | cut -f 2 -d "=" | tr -d "\n"
	  module_description Conexiones abiertas (interval 2)
	  module_end
	  
	  # Free space on disk
	  module_begin
	  module_name FreeDiskC
	  module_type generic_data
	  module_freedisk C:
	  module_description Free space on drive C:
	  module_end
	  
	  # CPU usage percentage
	  module_begin
	  module_name CPUUse0
	  module_type generic_data
	  module_cpuusage 0
	  module_description CPU#0 usage
	  module_end
	  
	  module_begin
	  module_name FreeMemory
	  module_type generic_data
	  module_freememory
	  module_description Amount of free memory.
	  module_end
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

