<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-15"?> 

<chapter id="chapter6">
  <title>System audit</title>
  
  <para>
    The Pandora's system audit shows all the actions performed by each
    user, as well as the failed logins.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The system audit includes actions that somehow try to by pass the 
    security system: attempts to delete an incident by an unauthorized 
    user, attempts to change user profiles by unauthorized users, etc.
    Its main function is, however, to trace the user connections 
    (login/logout).
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The audit Logs can be found in the "System Audit Log" option of the
    Administration menu, ordered chronologicly.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Filters can be applied to the Logs displayed to show only those of
    interest for the user, selected by the action the Log produces.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The selectable actions are those actions stored in the Data Base
    at that time.
  </para>
  
  <graphic scale='70' fileref="images/image049.png" valign="bottom" 
	   align="center"/>
  
  <para>
   The following fields display the Audit Logs information:
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis>User:</emphasis> User that triggerd the event (SYSTEM 
   is special user of the system).
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
   <emphasis>Action:</emphasis> Action generated by the entry in 
   the log.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
   <emphasis>Date:</emphasis> Date of the entry in the log.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <emphasis>Source IP:</emphasis> IP of the machine or the agent 
    that provoked the entry.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <emphasis>Comment:</emphasis> Comment describing the entry
    </para> 
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <sect1 id="sec6.1">
    <title>Statistics</title>
    <para>
      There isn't a special section to view system audit
      statistics. However, we could use a graph generated in the Users
      section to evaluate the actions of each user, as this graph
      would represent the total number of entries in the audit log for
      each one: the more active the user is the higher the number of
      entries.
    </para>
    <para>
      The graph will also show entries of invalid users, i.e., those
      entries generated by failed attemps to log in.
    </para>
    <graphic fileref="images/image050.png" valign="bottom" 
	     align="center"/>
  </sect1>
</chapter>