<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Introduction to Pandora</title>
  <sect1><title>Pandora. The Free monitoring system</title>
  <para>
    Pandora is a monitoring application to watch systems and
    applications. Pandora allows to know the status of any element of
    your bussiness systems. Pandora watch for your hardware, your
    software, your multilayer system and of course your Operating
    System. Pandora could detect a network interface down and the
    movement of any value of the NASDAQ new technology market. If you
    want, Pandora could sent a SMS message when your systems
    fails... or when Google value low below 330$.
  </para>
  <para>
    Pandora adapt, like an octopus, to your systems and requirements,
    because has been designed to be open, modular, multiplattform and
    easy to customize.
  </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introducing Pandora.</title>
    <para>
      &pandora; is a monitoring tool that allows a system
      administrator to visually analise the status and efficiency of
      Operating Systems, Servers, Applications and Hardware Systems -
      such as firewalls, proxies, databases, Web servers, tunnelling
      servers, routers, switches, processes, services, remote access
      servers, etc. - all integrated into an open and distributed
      architecture.  Pandora can be implemented over any operating
      system, with specific agents for each platform. Pandora can also
      monitor any TCP/IP hardware system, such as load balancers,
      routers, switches, printers, etc.
      <graphic fileref="images/esquema.png" scale="50" align="center"/>
      Pandora architecture is formed of four main components:
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Web Console</emphasis>: Pandora's user
	  interface. The user controls and operates the system with
	  it. Several Web consoles can be implemented in a single
	  system. The Web console is written in PHP, and rests on a
	  database and a Web server. It is compatible with any
	  platform - GNU/Linux, Solaris, Win2000, AIX, etc. However,
	  the official supported platform is GNU/Linux.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The console permits the user to control the status of the
	  agents, view statistical information, generate graphs and
	  data tables, keep a system incident control, as well as to
	  generate reports and change the alerts, agents, and user
	  profile settings.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Server</emphasis>: In Pandora 1.2 there are three 
	  different servers:
  	</para>
	<para>
	  The core server is the receptor of the data packages and 
	  generates the alerts - it is the brain of the system. 
	  Several servers can work alongside for larger systems. 
	  The core server accesses Pandora database, which is shared
	  with the Web server, and stores the processed data
	  packages. Server executes as daemon, and processes the
	  packages stored in its file system. Data is generated by the
	  system agents. Despite the server's low system resources
	  comsumption and simple installation and operation, the core
	  server is the most critical element of the system. The core
	  server receives and processes the produced data, and fires
	  the alerts and the events.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The Network Servers monitorize remote systems using
	  network resources like ICMP, TCP, UDP or SNMP
	  Queries. Network Servers are acting itself like "Network
	  Agents". This server fires the alerts and the events for this
	  modules.
        </para>
	<para>
	  The SNMP Server receives and processes the snmp traps, and fires
	  the alerts associated to it.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Central Database</emphasis>: At the moment the
	  system only supports MySQL. The central database keeps all
	  the information Pandora needs to work - agent data,
	  settings, user information, incidents, system settings,
	  etc. The system can use a MySQL cluster to store the
	  information, or a high disponibility solution for larger
	  sytems.
	</para>
	<para>
	  This database can work with any of the platform officially
	  supported by MySQL. Pandora can be implemented with MySQL
	  versions 3.0 and 4.0, although the latest is recommended.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Pandora Agents</emphasis>: They collect all the
	  system's data. They are executed in each local system,
	  although they can also collect remote information by
	  intalling monitoring sytems for the agent in several
	  different machines - called satellite agents.
	</para>
	<para>
	  They have been developed to work under a specific platform,
	  making use of the specific tools of the used language:
	  ShellScripting for Unix - which includes GNU/Linux, Solaris,
	  AIX, HP-UX and BSD, as well as the Nokia's IPSO. Pandora
	  agents can be developed in virtually any language, given its
	  simple API and being open source. Windows agent are
	  developed in a free development enviroment for C++ and uses
	  the same interface and modularity than Unix agents.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The old agent for Windows plattforms was developed on VBS
	  Scripting language, and is deprecated with the new Pandora
	  1.2 windows agent.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
       <graphic fileref="images/pandora_arch1.jpg" scale="70" align="center"/>
    </para>   
    </sect1>
  <sect1><title>What kind of systems/ services can be monitored?</title>
  <para>
    At present, with Pandora any process or system that through a
    command returns a value can be monitored, as well as any value in
    any Operating System log file or similar. Some examples of already
    existing implementations can be the following ones:
    <programlisting>      
      Number of connections (sessions) of Checkpoint FW-1
      Number of NAT sessions of Checkpoint FW-1
      Number of connections of Linux NetFilter / IPTables firewall
      Number of FW-1 logged packets 
      Number of FW-1 dropped packets 
      Number of FW-1 accepted packets
      State of High Availability in FW1 NG
      Last policy installed in a Firewall-1 module
      Synchronization state of the modules in FW1 NG
      CPU of the system: idle, user and system
      Number of processes of the system
      Temperature of the CPU of a system
      Value of a MS Windows registry entry
      Queued jobs in a generic dispatcher
      Memory of the system: free, swap, kernel Fw-1, cache
      Percentage of free space on disc (for different partitions)
      Messages processed by a mail gateway
      Existence of a string in a text file
      IP traffic (filtering based on the connections of the firewall)
      Hits of pages in HTTP Servers (Apache, iPlanet, IIS, Netscape)
      Percentage of erroneous packets in a Gateway
      Connections established in a Remote Access Server (RAS)
      Size of a file
      Open sessions by a VPN server
      MySQL Performance: Threads, queries, sessions...
      Snort system state
      Reported events by IDS (Snort) up to six levels of priority
      Network load
      Number of local Connections (TCP, UDP, Unix sockets)
      Detected viruses by a Web Antivirus Gateway
      ICMP latency time towards a host
      Rate of average transference in a file transfer tool
      Number of DNS requests attended by a server (including types)
      Number of FTP sessions attended by a FTP server
      (Generic) State of any active process / service in the system
      (Generic) State of any countable parameter of the system
    </programlisting>
  </para>
  <sect2><title>Global architecture</title>
  <para>
    Pandora 1.2 has changed many things from 1.1 version, but this
    graph representing Pandora architecture is very useful to
      understand in a single graph, all components.
      <graphic fileref="images/pandora_arch2.jpg" scale="45" align="center"/>
  </para>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1><title>Information gathering with Pandora agents</title>
  <para>
    Pandora agents are based on native languages in every platform:
    scripts that can be written in any language. It's possible to
    reproduce any agent in any programming language and can be
    extended without difficulty the existing ones in order to cover
    aspects not taken into account up to the moment.
  </para>
  <para>
    These scripts are formed by modules that each one gathers a
    "chunk" of information. Thus, every agent gathers several "chunks"
    of information; this one is organized in a data set and stored in
    a single file, called data file.
  </para>
  <para>
    The process of transferring the data file from the agent to the
    server is made regularly at a defined time interval in the agent
    configuration file, pandora_agent.conf. It's possible to modify
    that parameter to not fill the database with non-relevant
    information, not to load the network or to not affect the system
    performance. The default interval is 300 (seconds), which is
    equivalent to five minutes. Minor values of 100 (seconds) are not
    recommended since host performance can be affected, besides
    loading excessively Database and the Operating System of Pandora
    Server. Pandora is not a real time system; it's an applications
    and systems general monitoring system in environments that are not
    critical at real time.
  </para>
  <para>
    Packets transfers are made via SSH, with DSA authentication
    (although also RSA can be used). The process is completely safe
    since neither any password nor unencrypted confidential
    information is sent. Confidentiality, integrity and authentication
    of the connections between the agent and the server are
    ensured. In the Agents and Server Installation and Configuration
    guides, the process of generation of keys to do the automatic SCP
    transfer is detailed.
  </para>
  <para>
    Also the transfer via FTP or any other file transfer system could
    be made, although SSH has been chosen for security and
    compatibility with most of the systems in the market.
  </para>
  <para>
    Pandora Agents are thought to be executed from the agent from
    which they gather information, although the agents can gather
    information of accessible machines from the host where they are
    installed. In this case those agents are called "Satellite
    Agents". These Satellite Agents can use Telnet, SNMP or any other
    commands to get the information.
  </para>
  <para>
    We can also have a host with several agents: Some that gather
    information from the accessible machines (acting as "satellite
    agents") and the Standard Agent that monitors the host where it's
    running.
  </para>
  <sect2><title>XML Data files</title>
  <para>
    The data file has the following syntax:
    <programlisting>
      hostname.serialnumber.data 
    </programlisting>
    This is an XML file, and its name is the combination of the
    hostname where the agent runs, a different serial number for every
    data package and the extension .data that indicates that it's a
    data file.
  </para>
  <para>
    We also have a control file for every data file:
    <programlisting>
      hostname.serialnumber.checksum
    </programlisting>
    This file has .checksum extension and contains a MD5 hash of the
    data file. This allows checking that the information has not been
    changed before being processed.
  </para>
  <para>   
    The XML data file generated by every agent is the core of
    Pandora. This file has the information gathered by the Agent. Its
    easy structure allows that any user could create it's own
    developments to be processed in Pandora, or use the included ones.
    An example of the information included into the data file is the
    following one:
  <screen>
    <![CDATA[
    <agent data os_name="SunOS" os_version="5.8" timestamp="300"
    agent_name="pdges01" version="1.0">
      <module>
        <name>SSH Daemon</name>
        <type>generic_proc</type>
        <data>1</data>
      </module>
      <module>
        <name>FTP Daemon</name>
        <type>generic_proc</type>
        <data>0</data>
      </module>
      <module>
        <name>DiskFree</name>
        <type>generic_data</type>
        <data>5200000</data>
      </module>
      <module>
        <name>UsersConnected</name>
        <type>generic_data_inc</type>
        <data>119</data>
        <min>1</min>
        <max>250</max>
        <description>Users currently connected</description>
      </module>
      <module>
        <name>LastLogin</name>
        <type>generic_data_string</type>
        <data>slerena</data>
      </module>
    </agent_data>
    ]]>
  </screen>
  </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2><title>Pandora servers</title>
  <para>
    With Pandora 1.2 version, you have three different types of servers:
    <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Pandora Data Server</emphasis>. This is a PERL
	  application that that processes the information sent by the
	  agents. The agents send the XML data file via SSH and the
	  server periodically verifies if it has new data files
	  waiting to be processed. You can setup different data
	  servers in different systems or in the same host (that will
	  be different virtual servers).
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Pandora Network Server</emphasis>. This is a PERL
	  application that execute network tasks like sending pings,
	  TCP requests, SNMP requests and UDP request. When you assign
	  an agent to a server, you are assigning to a network server,
	  not a data server, so, this is very important that machines
	  running network servers have "network visibility" to hosts
	  assigned in network modules.
	</para>
	<para>
	  For example, if you create a module to make a ping check to
	  192.168.1.1 and assign this agent/module to a server in a
	  192.168.2.0/24 network without access to 192.168.1.0/24
	  module always report DOWN. 
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Pandora SNMP Server</emphasis>. This is a PERL
	  application that parse output from standard snmptradp (we
	  provide one binary for snmptrapd, but its possible you need
	  to replace it with a binary that runs better in your
	  system). This daemon receives SNMP traps, and Pandora SNMP
	  Server stores in database and fire alerts assigned in
	  Pandora SNMP Console.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    Data are extracted from the data file, identifying origin, type
    and category. One classified, the data are inserted into the
    Database by the same Perl script.
  </para>
  <para>
    Pandora Server can work in High Availability and/or Load
    Balancing. In a very big architecture, several Pandora Servers can
    be arranged simultaneously to be able to manage big volumes of
    information distributed by geographical or functional zones.
  </para>
  <para>
    Pandora Server is always running (as a daemon) and permanently
    verifies if some element causes to fire an alarm. If so, it
    executes the action defined in the alarm, as to send a SMS, an
    email, to activate the execution of a SCRIPT or to send an HTTP
    form.
  </para>
  <para>
    We could have several simultaneous servers, one of them is the
    Main Server or "Master Server " and the rest servers are "Slave
    Servers". The Master Server is the only one that verifies the
    alarms if any agent goes down. The server who receives the data
    file from the agent always fires the rest of alarms, defined in
    the agents' modules. This is also important if this server changes
    (due to configurations of high availability, load balancing or
    clustering).
  </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2><title>Pandora console</title>
  <para>
    The Web Console it's a web application that allows to see
    graphical reports, state of every agent, and to access to the
    information sent by the agent, to see every monitored parameter
    and to see its evolution throughout the time, to form the
    different nodes, groups and users of the system. It is the part
    that interacts with the final user, and that allows you to
    administer the system.
  </para>
  <para>
    The Web Console is written in PHP and no plug-in, Flash, Java or
    ActiveX is needed to access the console, only a browser that
    supports HTML and CSS (IE5+ o Mozilla 4+). Pandora Web Console can
    run in several servers, the only thing you need is to access
    Pandora Database, where Pandora stores all the information.
  </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2><title>Pandora database</title>
  <para>
    Pandora uses a SQL Database to store all the information. Pandora
    maintains an asynchronous database with all the received data,
    making a temporary cohesion of everything what it receives and
    normalizing all the information from the different sources. Every
    Agent data module generates an entry of information for every data
    bundle, which implies that a real production system can have of
    the order of ten million of data, or information atoms.
  </para>
  <para>
    This information is managed automatically from Pandora, carrying
    out a periodic and automatic maintenance of the database. This
    allows that Pandora should need neither any type of administration
    of database nor process attended by an operator or manager. This
    is made by a periodic purge of the past information over a date
    (by default 90 days), as well as a data compaction of the data
    that have more than, by default, 30 days.
  </para>

  <sect3><title>Compacting data</title>
  <para>
    Data stored by Pandora are useful to see evolutions regard through
    the time, to make statistics, to generate reports and to do
    capacity planning, as well as other tasks of statistical
    nature. For it, it isn't necessary to have all the data, but it's
    enough to have a representative sample, of smaller resolution,
    enough to carry out the task that is needed.
  </para>
  <para>
    With that philosophy the compaction system has been
    constructed. If we have a sample of 9.000 elements, distributed
    during 90 days, for example, Pandora is going to take the data of
    last month, which would be 3.000 elements and it's going them to
    compress them in 300. In the graphs they will practically be seen
    equal, which it will serve us for the reports, statistics and
    other tasks. This is made by means of interpolation in temporary
    strips, in a totally automatic and periodic way, without the user
    or the administrator must himself or herself worry about it.
  </para>
  </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
  <title>Pandora 1.2 new features</title>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Alert system</emphasis>. Now its possible to define a
    "minimun" and "maximum" limit to fire an alert, just to delete
    "noisy" data that fires false positives.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Network Subsystem</emphasis>. Now its possible to
    monitor and analyze data using remote network tools, without using
    agents, from the new Pandora Network Server component. All
    management are made from Pandora Console, and now you will be able
    to make ICMP checks (Ping), size network latency, get all types of
    SNMP values (including scanning MIB), and makes TCP/UDP
    connections to check ports, and test text applications, sending
    texts and waiting for a specific response.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Module groups.</emphasis>Modules now could be grouped
    using a new "module groups".
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Network data refresh on demand.</emphasis> Could
    be for each module or using a "global group refresh", forcing
    Pandora Network Servers to refresh all network modules inside a
    group.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Online contextual help</emphasis>, for Pandora WEB Console.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>New Pandora server infraestructure.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>New SNMP trap console</emphasis> to receive SNMP traps
    and assigning alerts.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Internal messaging system</emphasis>, to notify events
    to Pandora users.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Agent detail view autorefresh</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>New main agent group view</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Improved database management system</emphasis>, that
    allows to manage much more data.
  </para>  
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>About Pandora
  </title>
  <para>
    Pandora is a project initiated and mainly developed by Sancho
    Lerena, at present other people is working on it: Raul Mateos,
    David Villanueva, Esteban Sanchez, Jose Navarro and Jonathan
    Barajas. We want to give thanks for many other people who help us
    with translation, graphic design, bugs reporting and interesting
    ideas.
  </para>
  <para>
    Pandora is Free Software, and is published under GPL Licence. In
    order to know the last features, go to the official web site of
    the project in http://pandora.sourceforge.net.
  </para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
