<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 

<chapter id="chapter9">
	<title>Pandora Configuration</title>

	<para>All the configurable parameters in Pandora can be set in the 
	"Pandora Setup" section, in the Administration menu.</para>

	<graphic fileref="images/image051.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para>These parameters are:</para>

	<para><emphasis>Language:</emphasis> In following versions or revisions 
	of the actual Pandora version will support more languages. 
	At the moment version 1.2 supports English, Spanish, Bable, Italian, 
	French, Catalan and Portuguese of Brazil.
	</para>
	<para><emphasis>Page block size:</emphasis> Maximum size of the lists 
	in the event, incident and audit log sections.
	</para>
	<para><emphasis>Max. days before compact data:</emphasis> This parameter 
	controls data compacting. From the number of days in this parameter the 
	data starts getting compacted. For large amounts of data it is recommended
	to set this parameter to a number between 14 and 28; for systems with 
	less data load or very powerful systems, a number
	between 30 and 50 will be enough.
	</para>
	<para><emphasis>Max. days before purge:</emphasis>
	This parameter controls how long the data is kept
	before it is permanently deleted. The recommended value is 60. 
	For systems with little resources or large work load the recommended value 
	is between 40 and 50.
	</para>
	<para><emphasis>Graphic resolution (1 low, 5 high):</emphasis>
	This value represents the precision of the
	interpolation logarithm to generate the graphics.
	</para>
	<para><emphasis>Compact interpolation (Hours: 1 fine, 10 medium, 20 bad):</emphasis>
	This is the grade of compression used to compact the Data Base,
	being 1 the lowest compression rate and 20 the highest.
	A value above 12 means a considerable data loss.
	It's not recommended to use value above 6 if the data needs to be
	represented graphically in large time intervals.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="sec9.1">
		<title>Links</title>

		<para>Links to different Internet or private network links can be 
		configured in Pandora. These could be search engines, applications or 
		company Intranets.</para>

		<para>The links configured in Pandora can be edited through the 
		"Pandora Setup"&gt;"Links" option in the Administration menu.</para>

		<graphic fileref="images/image052.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

		<para>A new link is created by clicking on "Create".
		The link can be then edited:</para>

		<graphic fileref="images/image053.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
	</sect1>
</chapter>