<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 

<chapter>
  <title>Agents</title>

  <para>The agents collect information. The public key
  of the machine to be monitored needs to be copied onto Pandora and the agent
  executed. Pandora's server starts now receiving and processing the data
  collected by the agent. The data collected from the agents are called "modules".</para>

  <para>The value of each module it is the value of one
  monitored variable. The agent must be activated in Pandora's server and a group
  assigned to the agent. The data starts then been consolidated in the database
  and can be accessed.</para>

  <para>The user can:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>View the agent status</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Access to the collected information</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Access the monitored values and its evolution in time</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>View graphic reports</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Configure Alerts</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect1>
    <title>Group Manager</title>

    <para>Groups are added in "Manage Profiles" &gt; "Manage Groups", 
    Administration menu.</para>

    <graphic fileref="images/image007.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

    <para>There are nine default groups on this screen.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>Applications</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>Comms</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>Databases</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>Firewall</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>IDS</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>Others</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>Servers</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis>Workstations</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A group is added by clicking "Create group" and assigning
    a name to it.</para>
    <para>A group is deleted by clicking the delete icon 
    <graphic fileref="../../images/cancel.gif"/> 
    in the right hand side of each group.</para>
  </sect1>	
  <sect1>
    <title>Adding an agent</title>

    <para>Before an agent is added, the public key of the
    machine to be monitored needs to be copied. The agent is then executed, and
    added through the web console. The data starts now being consolidated in the
    Database and can be accessed.</para>

    <para>An agent is added in "Manage Agents" &gt; "Create agent" in the Administration menu.</para>

    <graphic fileref="images/image008.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

    <para>To add a new agent the following parameters must be configured:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Agent Name:</emphasis> Name of the agent. This and
	  the "agent name" parameter in Pandora's agent.conf file
	  <emphasis>must have the same value</emphasis>. If this
	  variable is commented out in the code, the name used will be
	  the name of the Host (to obtain this, execute the hostname
	  command).
	</para>
	
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>IP Address:</emphasis> IP address of an agent. An
	  agent can share its IP address with other agents.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Group:</emphasis> Pandora's group the agent belongs.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Interval:</emphasis> Execution interval of an
	  agent. It is the time elapsed between two executions.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>OS:</emphasis> The Operating System to be
	  monitored. The supported Operating Systems are: AIX, BeOS,
	  BSD, Cisco, HPUX, Linux, MacOS, Other, Solaris,
	  Windows.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Description:</emphasis> Brief description of an agent.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Module definition:</emphasis> There are two modes
	  for a module:
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  - <emphasis>Learning mode:</emphasis> All the modules sent by
	  the agent are accepted. They are automatically defined by the
	  system. It is recommended to activate the agents in this mode
	  and change it once the user is familiar with the system.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  - <emphasis>Normal mode:</emphasis> The modules in this mode
	  must be configured manually. The self  definition of the
	  modules is not allowed in this mode.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Disabled:</emphasis> This parameter shows if the
	  agent is activated and ready to send data or
	  deactivated. The deactivated agents don't appear in the user
	  views.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <sect2>
      <title>Assigning modules</title>

      <para>Pandora's agents use the operating system own commands to
      monitor a device. Pandora's server will store and process the
      output generated by those commands. The commandos are called
      "modules".</para>

      <para>If the agent had been added in "normal mode", the modules
      to be monitored should have been assigned. Those modules must be
      configured in the agent configuration file.</para>

      <para>The modules to be processed by Pandora's server are
      assigned in the "Manage Agents" option, Administration menu. A
      list with all the agents in Pandora will be shown here.</para>

      <para>You'll get a form with all the agent's settings when the
      agent name is clicked. In the same screen there is a section to
      assign modules.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image009.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>The following fields must be filled to create a
      module:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  <emphasis>Module type:</emphasis> This is the type of data
	  the module will process. There are five types of data:
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	  - <emphasis>generic_data></emphasis>, Integer data type -
	  <emphasis>generic_data_inc</emphasis>, Incremental integer
	  data type - <emphasis>generic_data_proc</emphasis>, Boolean
	  data type: 0 False, &gt;0 True -
	  <emphasis>generic_data_string</emphasis>, Alphanumeric data
	  type (text string, max. 255 characters)
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Module name:</emphasis> The name of the module
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Maximum:</emphasis> Upper threshold for the
	    value in the module. Any value above this threshold will
	    be taken as invalid and the whole module will be
	    discarded.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Maximum:</emphasis> Lower threshold for the
	    value in the module. Any value below this threshold will
	    be taken as invalid and the whole module will be
	    discarded.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Comments:</emphasis> Comments added to the module.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	All the modules to be monitored by an agent can be reviewed by
	accessing the agent in the "Manage Agents" option,
	Administration menu.
      </para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image010.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>
	In this screen the modules can be:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Deleted by clicking <graphic fileref="../../images/cancel.gif"/>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Edited by clicking <graphic fileref="../../images/config.gif"/>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	However, the type of data of the module can't be modified.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Alerts</title>

      <para>
	An alert is Pandora's reaction to an out of range module
	value. The Alert can consist in sending and e-mail or SMS to
	the administrator, sending a SNMP trap, write the incident
	into the system syslog or Pandora log file, etc. And basically
	anything that can be triggered by a script configured in
	Pandora's Operating System.
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Adding an Alert</title>

	<para>
	  The existing Alerts are accessed by clicking on the "Manage
	  Alerts" option, Administration menu.
	</para>
	<para>There are 6 default types of Alerts:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>eMail</emphasis>. Sends an e-mail from Pandora's Server
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Internal audit</emphasis>. Writes the incident
	      in Pandora's internal audit system
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>LogFile</emphasis>. Writes the incident in the log file</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>SMS Text</emphasis>. Sends an SMS to a given mobile phone</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>SNMP Trap</emphasis>. Sends a SNMP Trap</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Syslog</emphasis>. Sends an alert to the Syslog</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<graphic fileref="images/image011.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para>An Alert is deleted by clicking on the delete icon <graphic fileref="../../images/cancel.gif"/> placed on the right hand side of the Alert. A new customised Alert can be created clicking in "Create Alert".</para>

	<para>The values "_field1_", "_field2_" and "_field3_" in the customised Alerts are used to build the command line that the machine where Pandora resides will execute  if there were several servers, the one in Master mode.</para>

	<graphic fileref="images/image012.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para>When a new Alert is created the following field must be filled in:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Alert name:</emphasis> The name of the Alert</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Command:</emphasis> Command the Alert will trigger</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Description:</emphasis> Description of the Alert</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>In 'Command' data field these variables are used to build the command line that the machine where Pandora resides will execute  if there were several servers, the one in Master mode, replacing at runtime:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>_field1_</emphasis>: Field #1, usually assigned as username, e-mail destination or single identification for this event</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>_field2_</emphasis>: Field #2, usually assigned as short description of events, as subject line in e-mail</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>><emphasis>_field3_</emphasis>: Field #3, a full text explanation for the event</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>><emphasis>_agent_</emphasis>: Agent name</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>_timestamp_</emphasis>: A standard representation of date and time. Replaced automatically when the event has been fired</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>_data_</emphasis>: The data value that triggered the alert</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Assigning Alerts</title>

	<para>The next step after an Agent has been added, its modules have been configurated and the alerts have been defined, it is time to assign those Alerts to the agent.</para>

	<para>This is done by clicking on the Agent to be configured on the "Manage Agents" option, Administration menu. The Alert Assignation form is placed at the bottom of that page.</para>

	<graphic fileref="images/image013.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para>To assign an Alert the next fields must be filled in:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Alert type:</emphasis> This can be selected from the list of alerts that have been previously generated.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Maximum Value:</emphasis> Defines the maximum value for a module. Any value above that threshold will trigger the Alert.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Minimum Value:</emphasis> Defines the minimum value for a module. Any value below that will trigger the Alert.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Description:</emphasis> Describes the function of the Alert, and it is useful to identify the Alert amongst the others in the Alert General View.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Field #1 (Alias, name):</emphasis> Define the used value for the "_field1_" variable.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Field #2 (Single Line):</emphasis> Define the used value for the "_field2_" variable.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Field #3 (Full Text):</emphasis> Define the used value for the "_field3_" variable.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Time threshold:</emphasis> Minimum duration between the firing of two consecutive alerts, in seconds.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Max Alerts Fired:</emphasis> Maximun number of alerts that can be sent consecutively.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis>Assigned module:</emphasis> Module to be motitorized by the alert.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>All the alerts of an agent can be seen through "Manage Agents"
	in the Adminitration menu and selecting the agent.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Agent module and agent's alert management</title>

      <para>It might happen that the user finds that modules and alerts
      configured for an agent would be repeated in a new agent.</para>

      <para>In order to simplify the administrator's job Pandora offers
      the option of copying modules and alerts defined in an agent to be 
      assigned to another.</para>

      <para>The screen is accessed through "Manage Agents"&gt;
      "Manage Config.", in the Administration menu:</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image014.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>The Source Agent menu permits the selection of the agent
      where the needed modules and/or alerts reside. The "Get Info" 
      button shows the modules for that agent in the Modules list box.
      </para>

      <para><emphasis>The copy process</emphasis> is performed to copy 
      the module and/or alert configuration from the selected source 
      agents to the selected destination agents. Several agents can be
      selected, pressing CTRL and the mouse right button simultaneously. 
      The two tick boxes at the top of the form will be used to specify
      if the configuration to copy is from modules and/or from alerts.
      </para>

      <para><emphasis>The delete process</emphasis> is performed to delete the
      configuration of the destination agents, in the multiple selection 
      list box. Several agents can be selected at a time, and the tick 
      boxes at the top of the form indicate whether it is the modules
      or the alerts configuration what is to	be deleted. The
      application will prompt to confirm the deletion, as once 
      deletion is performed, the data associated to them will also be 
      deleted.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Agents group detail</title>

      <para>Once you have configured your groups and agents, you can 
      see the status of the groups of agents through "View Agents", 
      in the Operation Menu.</para>

      <para>If you pass the mouse over any group image, you'll see
      the number of agents of that group as well the number of monitors,
      organized by status.</para>

      <para>By pressing the icon 
      <graphic fileref="../../images/target.gif"/> 
      at the right of any group image, you will update the info of 
      that group.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Agent monitoring </title>

    <para>When the agents start the data transmission to the server,
    and it is added in the Web console, Pandora processes and inserts
    the data in the Database. The data are consolidated and can be
    accessed from the Web console, either as row data or as graphs.</para>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Agent view</title>

      <para>All the Agents can be accessed from the Operation menu.
      From here the status of the agents can be quickly reviewed thanks
      to a simple system of bulbs and coloured circles.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image015.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>The list of agents shows all the relevant the information
      in the following columns:</para>

      <para><emphasis>Agent:</emphasis> Shows the agent's name.</para>
      <para><emphasis>SO:</emphasis> Displays an icon that represents the
      Operating System.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Interval:</emphasis> Shows the time interval (seconds)
      in which the agent sends data to the server.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Group:</emphasis> This is the group the agent belongs to.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Modules:</emphasis> Under normal circumstances this field
      shows the values representing the number of modules and
      the number of monitors, both in black. If the status of a monitor 
      changes to "incorrect", one additional number is shown: the number 
      of modules, the number of monitors and the number of monitors with 
      "incorrect" status, all in black save the last one.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Status:</emphasis> Shows the "general" status of the agent
      through the following icons:</para>
      <para>
	<graphic fileref="../../images/b_green.gif"/> 
	All the monitors OK. It's the ideal status.
	<graphic fileref="../../images/b_white.gif"/> 
	No defined monitors. Sometimes nothing is monitored
	that could be right or wrong, and only numeric or 
	text data is reported.
	<graphic fileref="../../images/b_red.gif"/> 
	At least one of the monitors is failing. Usually we
	want to avoid this, and keep our systems in a healthy 
	green colour.
	<graphic fileref="../../images/b_blue.gif"/> The agent 
	doesn't have any data. New agents with an empty data
	package can have this status.
	<graphic fileref="../../images/b_yellow.gif"/> Colour 
	shifting from green to red. This icon indicates
	that the agent has just changed its status, from 
	'All OK' to 'we have a problem'.
	<graphic fileref="../../images/b_down.gif"/> When an agent
	is down or there is no news from it for 2 times the Interval
	value in seconds. Usually it is due to a communication issue
	or a crashed remote system.>
      </para>
      <para><emphasis>Alerts:</emphasis> Shows if any alerts have been sent 
      through the following icons:</para>
      <para>
	<graphic fileref="../../images/dot_green.gif"/> 
	No alerts have been sent.
	<graphic fileref="../../images/dot_red.gif"/> 
	When at least one alert has been sent within 
	the time threshold of the alert.
      </para>
      <para><emphasis>Last contact:</emphasis> Shows the time and date of the 
      last data package sent by the agent, using a progress bar, 
      according to value of the interval. If you see the image 
      <graphic fileref="../../images/outof.gif"/>, 
      the agent has not send data during the interval. 
      Passing the mouse over the image will show you the last contact 
      in time and date format.</para>

      <para><emphasis>Note:</emphasis> The icon 
      <graphic fileref="../../images/setup.gif" width="15"/> 
      is only visible if you're and administrator and it's a link 
      to the "Manage Agents" &gt; "Update Agent" option in the 
      Administration menu.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Accessing the data of an agent</title>

      <para>When an agent is accessed, by clicking on its name, all the
      information related to that agent is displayed.</para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Agent general info</title>

	<para>This shows the data introduced when the agent was created 
	and the total number a data packages the agent has sent.</para>

	<graphic fileref="images/image016.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Last data received</title>

	<para>This is the description of all the agent modules 
	been monitored.</para>

	<graphic fileref="images/image017.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para>In this list the module information is shown
	in the following columns:</para>

	<para><emphasis>Module name:</emphasis> Name given to the module
	in the agent's config file.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Module type:</emphasis> Type of module as described
	in Asigning Modules section.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Description:</emphasis> Description given to the module
	in the agent's config file.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Data:</emphasis> Last data sent by the agent.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Graph:</emphasis> Monthly(M), Weekly(W), Daily(D)
	and Hourly(H) graphs are generated with
	the data sent by the agent against time.</para>

	<para>On the left hand side of the graph the newst
	data is represent, and on the right had side the oldest.</para>

	<para>The generated graphs are:</para>
	<para> - <emphasis>Hourly graph</emphasis> 
	(<graphic fileref="../../images/grafica_h.gif"/>)
	covers a 60 minute interval</para>
	<graphic fileref="images/image018.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para> - <emphasis>Daily graph</emphasis> 
	(<graphic fileref="../../images/grafica_d.gif"/>) 
	covers a 24 hour interval</para>
	<graphic fileref="images/image019.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para> - <emphasis>Weekly graph</emphasis> 
	(<graphic fileref="../../images/grafica_w.gif"/>) 
	covers a 7 day interval</para>
	<graphic fileref="images/image020.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para> - <emphasis>Mothly graph</emphasis> 
	(<graphic fileref="../../images/grafica_m.gif"/>) 
	covers a 30 day interval</para>
	<graphic fileref="images/image021.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para><emphasis>Raw Data:</emphasis> This is the raw data sent by the agent</para>

	<para> - <graphic fileref="../../images/data_m.gif"/> Last month</para>
	<para> - <graphic fileref="../../images/data_w.gif"/> Last week</para>
	<para> - <graphic fileref="../../images/data_d.gif"/> Last day</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Complete list of monitors</title>

	<para>This is the description of all the monitors defined by
	the agent</para>

	<graphic fileref="images/image022.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para>The list shows the information about the monitors in the
	following columns:</para>

	<para><emphasis>Agent:</emphasis> Agent where the monitor is defined.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Type:</emphasis> Data type of the monitor. For a monitor this
	value is always of the generic_proc type.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Module name:</emphasis> Name given to the module when it was
	created.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Description:</emphasis> Description given to the module
	in the agent's config file.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Status:</emphasis> The table shows the agent status through
	the	following icons:</para>

	<para><graphic fileref="../../images/b_green.gif"/> 
	The monitor is OK</para>
	<para><graphic fileref="../../images/b_red.gif"/> 
	The monitor is failing</para>

	<para><emphasis>Last contact:</emphasis> Shows the time and date of 
	the last data packaged received from the agent</para>

      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Complete list of alerts</title>

	<para>This is the description of all the alarms defined 
	in the agent</para>

	<graphic fileref="images/image023.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

	<para>The monitor information is shown in the list 
	divided in the following fields:</para>

	<para><emphasis>ID:</emphasis> Agent were the alert has been defined.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Type:</emphasis> Type of alert.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Description:</emphasis> Description given to the alert when 
	it was created.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Last fired:</emphasis> The last time the alert was 
	executed.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Times Fired:</emphasis> Number of times the alert was 
	launched.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Status:</emphasis> Shows if the alert has been sent through 
	the following icon:</para>

	<para><graphic fileref="../../images/dot_green.gif"/> No alerts 
	have been sent</para>
	<para><graphic fileref="../../images/dot_red.gif"/> At least 
	one alert has been sent</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Group details</title>

      <para>The groups configured in Pandora can be
      accessed through "View Agents"&gt;"Group detail" in the 
      Operation menu. The group details can be reviewed quickly thanks 
      to a system of coloured bulbs.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image025.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>The groups are displayed ordered by the following columns:</para>

      <para><emphasis>Groups:</emphasis> Name of the group</para>
      <para><emphasis>Agents:</emphasis> Number of agents configured 
      in the group.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Monitors:</emphasis> Number of monitors configured 
      in the group.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Status:</emphasis> The status is described through 
      the following icons:</para>

      <para><graphic fileref="../../images/b_green.gif"/> 
      All monitors are OK.</para>
      <para><graphic fileref="../../images/b_red.gif"/> 
      At least one monitor has failed.</para>
      <para><graphic fileref="../../images/b_down.gif"/> 
      At least one monitor is down and there is no contact
      with it.</para>
      <para><graphic fileref="../../images/b_white.gif"/> 
      This Agent doesn't have any monitor defined.</para>

      <para><emphasis>OK:</emphasis> Number of monitors that are OK.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Failed:</emphasis> Number of failing monitors.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Down:</emphasis> Number of down monitors.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Monitors view</title>

      <para>The description of all the monitors defined in the server
      can be viewed from the "View Agents"&gt;"Monitor detail" 
      option in the Operation menu.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image026.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>In this list all the monitors appear in a similar way as
      in the individual view, but now they are shown all together. 
      This allows a deeper analisys of each monitor.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Alert details</title>

      <para>The description of all the alerts defined in the server 
      can be viewed from the "View Agents"&gt;"Alert Details" 
      option in Operation menu.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image027.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>In this list all the alerts appear in a similar way 
      as in the individual view, but now they are shown all together. 
      This allows a deeper analisys of each alert.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Data Export</title>

      <para>The Data Export tool can be found in the "View Agents"&gt;"
      Export data" option in the Operation Menu.</para>

      <para>Three parameters need to be configured for exporting data: 
      the agent where data resides, the modules to be exported 
      and the date interval of the data to be exported:</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image028.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>The fields in the results of Exporting data are:</para>

      <para><emphasis>Module:</emphasis> Module name.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Data:</emphasis> Data contained by the module.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Timestamp:</emphasis> Date and time of the the package 
      was sent by the agent.</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image029.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

      <para>Selecting the CSV format for the output, a text
      file with extension <emphasis>.csv</emphasis> is be created. The data 
      is qualified by single quotes
      and the fields separated by commas:</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/image030.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Statistics</title>

      <para>Two kinds of graphical statistics are displayed from the 
      "View Agents" &gt;"Statistics" option, in the Operation menu:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A graph with the number of modules configurated for each
	  agent</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A graph with number of packages sent by each Agent. 
	  A package is the number of values from the modules the agent 
	  sends after each time interval</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <graphic fileref="images/image031.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
      <graphic fileref="images/image032.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
      <graphic fileref="images/image033.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>SNMP Console</title>
    <para></para>
    <sect2>
      <title>SNMP Alerts</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>