<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-15"?> 

<chapter>
	<title>Users</title>

	<para>The definition of a user is based on the user's
	daily activity. One or more profiles can be assigned to a single user</para>

	<para>A profile is a list of actions a user can or
	cannot perform on a given group, e.g. "view incidents",
	"database management", etc
	</para>

	<para>Each user is given a number of groups of agents
	he/she has permission to access, as well as the administrative profile
	he/she will have in each group. Each user can belong to one or more
	groups, with an assigned profile for each of them.</para>

	<para>Agent belongs to a group and only one, sharing
	the group with agents of similar characteristics. Groups also contain
	incidents.</para>

	<para>Summarizing: User profiles in Pandora define which users can access
	Pandora as well as what each user can do. Groups define elements in common
	among various users. Each user could be in one or more groups at any one
	time. Each group has user profiles which are defined and attached to it.
	A profile is a list of things a user can do, such as view incidents,
	manage database or other.</para>

	<sect1>
		<title>Profile manager</title>

		<para>Pandora's profile manager is used to assign specific profiles
		to each user. A hierarchy of users is so created, structured by the
		user's profile within the company. With this system different security
		levels can be implemented: read-only users, agent group coordinators 
		or system administrators.</para>

		<para>A profile is created from the Profile Manager tool in the
		Administration menu. There are five predefined profiles:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Operator (Read)</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Operator (Write)</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Chief Operator</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Group coordinator</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Pandora Administrator</para>
		    </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>To create a new profile click on "Manage Profiles"&gt;
		"Create Profile" in the Administration Menu</para>

		<graphic fileref="images/image002.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

		<para>Any of the following roles can be assigned to a new profile:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>View incidents (IR)</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Edit incidents (IW)</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Manage incidents (IM)</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>View agents (AR). To view agents as well as the events
			  generated by them</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Edit agents (AW). To modify then agent's modules</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Edit alerts (LW). To modify the alerts assigned to an agent</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Manage users (UM). To modify users and their roles</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Manage DB (DM). To modify the configuration and data
			  of the database (Global)</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Manage alerts (LM). To define new alerts (Global)</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>Manage Pandora (PM). To modify general system settings</para>
		    </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Adding a user</title>

		<para>A user is added clicking on "Manage Users"&gt;"Create user"
		in the Administration Menu</para>

		<para>To create a new user it is necessary to, at
		least, fill in the user ID, the password (twice) and Pandora's global profile.</para>

		<para>A global profile for a user maybe Administrator or Standard User.</para>

		<para>A user with an "Administrator" profile will have the highest
		security privileges in Pandora.</para>

		<graphic fileref="images/image003.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

		<para>Profiles must be assigned for each of the groups a new
		"standard" profile user can access, once the user is created
		and his configuration updated.</para>

		<graphic fileref="images/image004.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>

		<para>A user profile is deleted by clicking on the delete icon
		<graphic fileref="../../images/cancel.gif"/> on the right hand side
		of the profile.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Deleting a user</title>

		<para>A user is deleted by clicking on the delete icon
		<graphic fileref="../../images/cancel.gif"/> on the right hand
		side of the user. The list of users is accessed through the
		"Manage Users" option in the Administration menu.</para>

		<graphic fileref="images/image005.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Statistics</title>

		<para>The user activity statistics show a graph with the activity
		of the user, being the number of events the audit has generated
		for each user. The number of events of
		a user usually reflects the user's activity.</para>

		<para>Click on "View Users"&gt;"Statistics" in the Operation menu to show
		this graph:</para>

		<graphic fileref="images/image006.png" valign="bottom" align="center"/>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Messages to users</title>

		<para>To create a new message to other user, go to "Messages" section
		in the Operation menu. You can also read the received messages,
		but the sent messages are not stored.</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Messages to groups</title>
			<para>From "Messages"&gt;"Messages to groups" section in the
			Operation menu you can send messages to groups of users.
			The sent messages will not be stores.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>